then like
the there's a the creative act involves
expression. And expression comes from
experience. It comes from, you know, our
soul desiring to to connect with others.
AI doesn't have any of that. It has a
soul and it has a desire to connect.
It's It's And so, um and so when you
know, with if we if we leave it up to
if we if we start to replace humanity
with with machine
uh in this in this new way, I I think
that it can really open up a a series of
problems. So, we so, you know, um and to
put it over is really good about the
about putting it in its place uh and and
keeping it there, I think. That's That's
the framework I I think you have to
approach it with.
>> Lorenzo, Dave, thank you so much for
being with us today on this uh first day
of the Builders AI forum
um to talk about how um AI is changing
Catholic storytelling. Um maybe Dave, if
I could start with you
>> everyone has, you know, their own
reasons for telling stories uh
especially to Catholic audiences and all
that kind of stuff.
But uh we kind of arrived around three,
you know, important um
really the transcendentals, which are
truth, beauty, and goodness, you know?
We want to tell the truth about the
evangelization of the gospel. We want to
make sure it's accurate. It's It's the
right thing, right? Uh we want to make
sure that it's it's beautiful, that it's
aesthetically pleasing. It's actually,
you know, meeting people's standards
when it comes to what, you know, what we
expect from whatever media it might be.
Um and then, you know, uh that
that it's that it's that there's
something that's happening that's that's
positive and developmental for the
person who's actually encountering this
whatever the story is, right? That that
we're that we're being good stewards of
our audience actually in a way. Um you
know, uh the the classic example there
is of social media, right? Where we're
just, you know, it's like it's been
proven now that this is a a fairly
unhealthy thing for kids and even for
adults. And I I struggle with this
because I do social media professionally
and I use it a little bit
personally. And you know, and there's a
quite there's a tension there between
like, you know, is this something which
is it is it better to participate in
this thing that's not necessarily great
so that there is a faith component
available for people or is it better to
just remove ourselves entirely and hope
people kind of follow suit. Follow suit.
It's It's a It's difficult. But anyway,
these are some of the things that we
were grappling with today.
>> Um just a reality check for for our
audience. Um Lorenzo, when when you look
at AI today, like what can it actually
do practically in film today?
>> Yeah.
>> Mhm.
>> I mean, we're we're still in this time
where AI is it it's advancing like
crazy. Like there's a new update and
there's been some new drops recently
with with um Sora and whatnot. But um
you know, for us I think that the main
thing that we're seeing in AI is its
advantages in VFX.
So like if there's a big, you know, like
right now we're in front of a green
screen, um there's things you can do
with AI that make it a lot more
cost-efficient. Um there's also I've had
friends that have
full English movie that have dubbed the
voices in different languages to make it
more accessible, which is pretty crazy
cuz you could literally take my voice
and then change it to like Mandarin or
Italian or French.
>> And the lips change too, as much as
>> Yeah. No, it's nuts. It's absolutely
nuts.
So like things like that, you know, I
think
the uh old old-school filmmaker in me
it's it's like, you know, I still really
appreciate like we do animation and I I
really love hand-drawn
uh 2D animation. But we are seeing with
AI a lot of the efficiencies with, you
know,
development work where we can, you know,
get some some comps that we hey, we want
to create a show like this and then
we'll take it to a storyboard artist or
an animation
um artist and give him the look and feel
with the tone that we've generated from
from AI. So we, you know, our company is
utilizing a bit of AI. We're not
geniuses.
Um, but we're trying to learn and see
what others are doing and um, how to how
to find the balance. Does that make
sense?
>> No, no, absolutely. And when you I mean,
there's there's people talking about
like script generation, um, trans you
know, you mentioned translating,
editing, animation, and I've I've spoken
to a few friends, um, in Los Angeles who
you know, they they say that it's hard
for them, you know, at the time that the
industry is definitely going through a a
switch. Do you, um,
do you see something like like a like a
full-on AI film studio?
>> Yeah, we were talking about this a
little bit at the at the forum.
In my experience on what we're doing, I
I see that more on a in the in the
meantime, I see that living more on
short-form platforms like YouTube,
Instagram, Facebook. Um, as far as, um,
you know, bigger budget projects for
like studios and streamers, um, I don't
see it moving
that direction anytime soon. Um, but I I
think that'll be an an asset for it.
There's a lot of there's and it's in the
trades. Like if you look in Deadline
today, micro dramas are sort of popping
up. Um, and I think there will be some
an investment made into the micro dramas
and that AI can AI studios can develop
things for that particular, uh,
distribution platform.
>> And, um, how do you guys see, you know,
kind of I guess more of the traditional
secular media using AI in in you know,
in its aggressive modes and also just
experimenting it and how do you see that
different differing with the Catholic or
Christian audiences and Christian
entertainment and film?
>> I mean, AI AI usage is getting more and
more prolific with everything, right? I
think I heard a stat today that, uh, 60%
of commercials are are of the biggest
companies are now being using in Canada
are now using AI to create the
commercials and that when studying it
that, uh, I think that there has been 0%
less intent to buy based on
based on the one based on you know those
those commercials using AI to be
generated. And so and so it's it's
actually like not even
who
if if the company is just motivated by
you know the bottom line right if it's
just a greed based revenue model let's
be honest calling it what it is right
then then what could you not right you'd
be you'd be if if you're if you answer
to your shareholders and that's all they
care about then then you would be you'd
be irresponsible not to do that right
and so that
and so how does that differ from you
know the Catholic world really depends
on the on the creator right there's no
you know
thankfully I think it's a good thing
actually that that we have agency like
this it's not like the pope says
something and now everyone you know who
falls in line exactly with however we
approach you know this is we're talking
about art right or at least we're
talking about create creativity
and and so it really depends on the on
the person I think I think responsible
AI creators
or responsible AI users let's say
are are thinking deeply about what it
what what is lost both both from the not
just from the product standpoint of
what's created but from the process
standpoint of of what the what the
artist is maybe not going through as
they as they type in a a query or or or
a prompt rather than actually kind of
grapple with
you know the the crucible of making art
>> Where where do you feel that that the AI
could be you know
actually enhance the creative aspect of
this versus being kind of you you you
you offload that responsibility it's
almost a crutch you kind of
>> I
my my mind first goes to variety of
experience
so you know let's say in the ideation
stage of a project you are just talking
through you know you're brainstorming
what do what do we what do we want to do
for this particular scene or this
particular project or whatever it may be
and you're getting you're getting the
input from the people that you directly
work with and that's a beautiful thing.
That's that's person-to-person and you
know, it's as it's as unmediated as as
work can get, you know, between people.
Um but you only have available to you on
your on your little team, whoever
happens to be there, right? And it's
unlikely that you have a finished person
and it's unlikely that you also have a,
you know, a sister, you know, like what
what you just may want a lot more
perspectives. And so I so I think that's
one virtuous thing about AI is to be
able to in the brainstorming process to
be able to pull perspectives that you're
just not going to have access to
otherwise.
>> Yeah, research data, like you can
research things a lot better. Um
depending on which AI system you're
using, but um I think there's also the
the moral aspect of um you know, looking
at the encyclicals like Rerum Novarum
and and figuring out the Catholic
approach to treat AI, you know, like
with an artist and enhancing it cuz
you know, I mentioned this at the the
forum today, you could use AI to
storyboard out stuff or you know, get
some concept art.
But at the same time, you could like I
have friends that are Catholic
storyboard artists or Christians,
whatever denomination it is.
Um and they have children and they have
a a wife and you know, I feel called to,
you know, lean towards that direction of
of
you know, if I if I need a quick fix, I
could easily, you know, go on AI, but if
it's something, you know, where I can
spend more time with the development or
storyboards, you know, I I I would love
to invest in other people.
>> Absolutely, yeah.
>> You know.
>> How do how do we go about, you know,
kind of seizing this moment of
transformation? Um which feels unique
and go about making that that ecosystem
of of Catholic, you know, Catholic
studios, Catholic distributors
>> I mean, one of the things that we have
to keep in mind is just relegating tools
as tools and keeping them as tools,
right? And you know, Even the term tool
is a little bit crude. AI is so
sophisticated, right? And we're we're
way beyond
you know, Guardini's definition of what
a tool is. We're this is this is
certainly a machine or beyond, maybe. Um
but um but I think that's important
because it shouldn't be
it shouldn't
it it can augment, but it shouldn't
replace what a what a human should be
doing, right? Um and that's you going
back to what you said earlier, Ben, like
the there's a the creative act involves
expression. And expression comes from
experience. It comes from, you know, our
soul desiring to to connect with others.
AI doesn't have any of that. It has soul
and it has a desire to connect. It's
it's And so, um
and so when, you know, if if we we leave
it up to
if we if we start to replace humanity
with with machine uh in this in this new
way, I I think that it can really open
up a a series of problems. So, we So,
you know, um Antu Bad Nova is really
good about the about putting it in its
place uh and and keeping it there, I
think. Uh that's that's the framework I
I think you have to approach it with.
>> Mhm.
Yeah.
No, I I I I love that.
And if I'm if I'm asked in in point to
the Builders AI form, what what what are
you guys most excited about?
>> Yeah, no, I think it's just encouraging
to see other people um
wanting to come together to throw out
ideas and I think disagreement is good.
So, I think it's I think it's good to uh
that all of us are are are, you know,
the having healthy debates.
Um so, it's a it's a very encouraging
for me to um see other people, you know,
on on there's people here that are
entrepreneurs investing in AI. There's
filmmakers, there's journalists. So,
it's it's really encouraging to see all
all sorts of people come here to talk
about how the church can be at the
forefront and guide. I I really think
um there's a great encyclical
uh
by Pope Pius the 11th I believe
um
Vigilante Cura which talked about cinema
and media and journalists and it sort of
gave them the guidelines and
I think there would be a nice if there
could be a nice encyclical like that
where it gave them the guidelines
um
to how to implement AI and use it for
the good. Um so yeah it's crazy it's
crazy times we're living in.
>> Um but you know people are coming from
all different places and you're right
there's a lot of healthy discussion and
and debate. Um you know
one voice was was like hey the only
thing we have to fear I mean not to
quote it FDR but basically the the the
fear of using it. This is someone who is
really um
you know bullish on AI but when it comes
down to it you can get them into play
you
that person you know you can get them
into places where he'll say actually
this is this is really worrisome in in
areas because of because of the
potential for for
you know heresy at the extreme but just
just just wrong you know just just like
any tool.
Um
>> But like what is real?
>> Yeah what is real? Yeah like what yeah
we're heading into an area where you
know Blade Runner doesn't seem that
sci-fi anymore.
>> Deep fakes.
>> Oh my gosh.
>> Deep fakes are bad.
>> One thing that I've been I I I kind of
sign posted this earlier like one of the
things I've been struggling with is just
this idea of like
like what is the value of of people
scrolling on social media? You know
>> You're really hitting hard on that
tonight.
>> I you know I
>> You got some backlash.
>> I you know and rightly so because like I
I can see both ways. I mean look I
currently do this professionally. Like I
I am part of what might be a problem.
>> [laughter]
>> And that's part of it that's try that's
what I'm trying to grapple with is like
is it better you know to to play the
game so because here's here's here's
here's it's not it's not as innocuous as
it seems right? Like
yes people can post and people can look
on let's say Facebook right? Let's say
you're just scrolling through your
Facebook or your Instagram or whatever
your flavor is.
>> Yeah, uh you it seems innocuous enough
and okay, maybe you're using a little
more data on these off offset
on the in these offshore data centers
that you aren't even thinking about. So,
there's an environmental toll that
you're not thinking about and
whatever, there's there's that. But,
when you really play the game,
uh yeah, as a brand and you're trying to
reach your audience,
what when we post, I'm not looking for
people to just keep scrolling. Like like
my goal is not is not Facebook's goal,
right? I I don't I I'm not here
monetizing your eyeballs. As you know,
as when we post as a Diocese of Brooklyn
or whoever whether we're working with as
Inda Sales Media,
I'm posting because I'm trying to get
people to take a take a step in their in
their journey somehow, right? Their
spiritual journey. And so, if if if
that's the larger point, then I'm all
almost always trying to link off. It's
not just it's not just watch this and
move on.
When you when you when you post next to
your link, these walled garden companies
make it almost impossible for your own
audience who signed up to watch your
stuff to even see it, right? The the
algorithm takes it from like 4% chance
to like 1% chance just by including a
link.
Okay? And why do they do that? Because
they know you're they're going to lose
the eyeballs if they actually if if you
succeed at the at this call to action.
And so, what can I do? I can take out an
ad and pay them up front so that I'm
basically like paying them to allow me
to to remove this person from your
walled garden.
It's like so you lose either way. And
and and why am I trying to help, you
know, meta get bigger? Like that doesn't
that doesn't advance the church's cause.
And I and I don't even know if if what I
you know, it's it's just so it's
fraught.
>> But it but it seems that we would hit
kind of an existential cliff that if the
church isn't there on this pastoral
level and if we're not there as Catholic
storytellers really pointing to that,
that we could be in really, you know,
serious problems.
>> You know, the the the world kind of came
to this to this inflection point at it's
obviously Pope Leo the 14th choosing
that name uh was all about, you know,
the the the Industrial Revolution and
what he sees as the next revolution,
right? And um
the the the world is at this inflection
point at the end of that Industrial
Revolution, right? Like around, I don't
know, let's say 1920s-ish, like maybe a
little before. And the world needed to
decide like, okay, we have all this time
back from what the machines are now
doing that the that the people used to
do. And we can either uh lean into that
and say, all right, let's give people
like a break. Let's let's use this time
for recreation and like develop the
person. Or let's let's lean into greed
and just make people work just as much
as they always have if not more so that
we can raise those GDPs and all all
those, you know, those those signi-
those
the signals that we use for for wealth,
which is really great, right? And of
course the world chose that even though
the church was trying to
lead us uh the other way. And so, yeah,
so like in in some ways I do think that
um
the the idea of unearned time off sort
of thing, like there is a dignity in
work, right? Absolutely. Uh and so
people do need that. At the same time,
I don't even know if we're going to be
given that choice because I think the
world is going to is going to continue
to pivot toward greed. And I think that
like, yeah, this is just going to be
another way to be even more efficient
and and spend, you know, and like make
even more and and spend even more and
and yeah, it's just
I think I think it will be I mean, just
look at who's running the largest
models, right? It These are These are,
you know, Anthropic seems to be a little
more trustworthy, but it's not It It's
still coming from a place where, all
right, we raised 70 million and we're
going to have to pay it back. You know,
>> [clears throat]
>> like
>> I I think that's where you need um
to really start thinking about your your
and my brother and I've been speaking
about this a lot, our family rule of
life
um and family legacy
because there's going to come a point
where like what you said is everything's
going to be automated. But if you're
what you're building in your family and
what you're building in your business
can
um sort of combat those temptations of
leisure and just automate everything,
um it starts with the family and the
family is the building blocks of
society. So,
if you build branch out from that
network of like other good entrepreneurs
and other good families,
um you can start creating your own
ecosystems. You know, and that starts at
a local level, right? On you know,
principle subsidiary and
I think that's what is
I think there's going to be like a the
pendulum's going to go the other way.
I think it's going to go this way with
AI and technology and everything, but I
think there's going to be like a
renaissance of people wanting to get
back to the land, people wanting to
learn the ancient crafts. And so, as
much as we can utilize AI and its
advancements, which you know, there is
there's some good there. I think there's
also going to be a balancing act of
people wanting to have a simplistic way
of life and also
build family legacy
and pass down these things to your
children and talents to your children.
Um at least that's what we're trying to
build in in our in our family and our
company and we're trying to like include
our children at at the dinner table and
talk about future and what we're trying
to build as a family. And so, those are
the little things we're working on to
combat the craziness of of of life and
technology. And I wonder, A, when you
guys when uh David when you know, when
you're working in social media and then
Lorenzo of course in film, when you guys
are crafting your stories, when you're
crafting your messages, are you guys
changing it a little bit when you know
that that person A might just spend 30
seconds on it and it will be doing it
alone versus that thing of a cool, we
have that for you know, summer
blockbuster movie, we're going to we're
going to have that opening weekend,
everyone the grandparents to the the the
6-year-old is everyone's coming. Versus
now it's it seems very micro, you know,
okay, this is the audience that 30
seconds, cool, we got this many
impressions.
It seems a different sport.
>> I'll go first.
>> Yeah, sure. I mean, um you know, I I
would say the answer is yes and no. Um
you know, there
we are trying to
play the algorithm's game on social
media specifically, and and there's
there's ways to do that that we know we
Not only is it got, you know, that has
has to be less than 30 seconds on this
particular platform, but also it's got
to be square, and you know, whatever you
know, there's there's all these kinds of
things. Um but we're trying not to
always do that, right? We have There's a
We have a podcast we recently launched
called Religion to Reality, sh-
shameless plug. Uh and [laughter]
the where we where we let ourselves go,
right? We're not constrained by a a a
time limit, and some of the episodes are
almost an hour, right? And where where
and and I think there's a place for
that, right? As long as we recognize
like who our audience is. Um and so,
yeah, so I think it's yes and. I think
it's both.
>> Yeah, for us, I mean, we're For us, it's
either, you know, are we going straight
to the streaming platforms,
um or is this something that is worthy
of a theatrical audience or theatrical
uh film? So, it's Yeah, it's both and um
obviously, as a as a you know, born in
the '90s, the best experience is going
to the films,
>> gosh, yeah.
>> theaters, and um so, that's always the
That's always our first choice.
>> yeah.
>> Yeah, it's like, can we get the movie?
And there's such a beautiful experience,
you know, in in the in the theaters. So,
our preference is yes, we want to go
theatrical,
but it's, you know, it's risky these
days, and and you just have to have a
very smart business approach to if we go
theatrical, what do we need to do to
break even, or, you know, make X, Y, and
Z, and then, you know, there's there's
more opportunities on downstreaming
rights, where you have the first pay one
windows, where you you know, you can
start making more revenues, and the
second re-upping of the licensing, etc.
So,
um it just it really depends on what
your focus is, and what um your goal
with that individual asset is.
>> And Randall, if I may, I mean, this
might be impossible, but like, if you
look at the film industry now and you
look, you know, let's say I mean it it's
hard, but like in 10 years, I mean, what
what do you what do you hope it'll look
like in 10 years?
>> Yeah, I mean
Oh, that's a tough question.
Uh you know, in the in the next 10
years, I I hope there is more platforms,
distribution platforms. Um
you know, there's there's obviously you
have, you know, the big Warner Brothers,
Lionsgate, everyone and and and you have
companies like Angel Studios.
Um but I think there needs to be more
Angel Studios. I think there needs to be
more uh
better access for content creators to
have distribution.
Um so, I think in the next 10 years, if
there's uh more distribution platforms
um but also um young people learning
story, learning filmmaking, and that's
one of our goals is to, you know, have
interns and shepherd people where we can
build not just filmmakers cuz there are
great film schools, um but also how to
be an executive, how to pitch something,
how to raise money. Um I think we need
young executives to build them up into
higher positions. So, the next 10 years,
our goal is to, you know, train the next
generation, but to also have content for
multiple different different
distribution platforms.
>> Beautiful. What are your What are your
final hopes, I guess, for this for this
conference? And what do you hope, you
know, people then take out of it and go
out into the into the wider world with
with this energy?
>> Yeah. Um I mean, next tomorrow, we're
going to be covering kind of what we
think the guardrails need to be inside
kind of the the Christian storytelling
in media community. Uh what do what does
that look like? Like what How can we
avoid the risks basically of AI? Because
we want to be able to use this tool
responsibly, but what does that look
like? Without knowing really what the
future of this is, right? You know, if
you haven't read I've I've said this
today earlier, and I'll say it again. If
you haven't If you're a a parent and you
haven't read Jonathan Haidt's The
Anxious Generation, you need to because
basically proves why we shouldn't have
adopted social media before we
understood really what what was what was
going to happen because of it. And I'm
worried about AI in that same way. So,
these guardrails are super important.
And then and then after that, you know,
what are the next steps? Like what do we
actually hope can come next? And one of
the ideas that's been thrown out there
is some kind of manifesto that allows us
to to kind of put our you know, put our
point of view out there on on what we
think good Christian storytelling
consists of, aims to do, and how does it
do that?
>> Yeah, I
completely agree. Some some guardrails
and also um
I would just say
executing
uh
having prudence with everything that
you're doing.
Um so, that way I mean your your your
eternal salvation comes first. So, like,
you know, looking at AI through the lens
of is this good for my soul?
Will it help me get to heaven? Will it
you know, and then sort of branching out
that to towards business, towards family
life. So, just really
I hope everyone has you know, caution
cuz it's it's scary.
Um so, for me that's what I'm hoping
comes out of this forum is like, you
know, the the extreme prudence on how to
apply this to your life and to your
business.
>> Lorenzo, Dave, this has been wonderful.
Thank you so much for the work that
you're doing. It's very inspiring.
>> Thanks for having us. God bless.
>> Gratson. The first